<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Livingstone Online: Annotated African Ethnic Group List</title>
				<author>Adrian S. Wisnicki</author>
				<author>Megan Ward</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2017</date>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">(c) Livingstone Online. <ref
						target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons
						Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License</ref>.</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>A Livingstone Online project.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0001">
					<form>
						<orth>Baguha</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group whose descendants are now known as the Holoholo and who, in
						Livingstone's time, lived on the western shore of Lake Tanganyika in east Africa.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0016">
					<form>
						<orth>Bakwena</orth>
					</form>
					<def>A SeTswana speaking group in southern Africa. Livingstone became a missionary to the
						Bakwena (under the leadership of Sechele) in 1846.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0002">
					<form>
						<orth>Bemba</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also Awemba. African ethnic group based in the north-eastern part of present-day Zambia
						with historical links to the Luba and Lunda populations of the Kantanga region of the
						Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0003">
					<form>
						<orth>Bena</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in what is the south central part of Tanzania.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0004">
					<form>
						<orth>Bira</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in the Ituri rainforest in the north-eastern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0005">
					<form>
						<orth>Bungu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania and settled to the south east of Lake
						Rukwa.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0006">
					<form>
						<orth>Garaganza</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group from present-day Tanzania often included in the larger Nyamwezi
						group.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0007">
					<form>
						<orth>Gogo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in the central part of present-day Tanzania.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0008">
					<form>
						<orth>Kololo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Sotho people of southern Africa. Having been displaced by political upheaval in the early
						nineteenth century (known as the Mfecane), migrated north under the leadership of Sebituane
						and came to settle in the Zambesi River valley in present-day Zambia around 1840. Kololo
						porters, sent by chief Sekeletu, journeyed with Livingstone on his famous African
						transcontinental journey.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0009">
					<form>
						<orth>Lega</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in the rainforests of the eastern part of present-day
						Democratic Republic of the Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0017">
					<form>
						<orth>Luba</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group from the central part of present-day Democratic Republic of the
						Congo, whose kingdom constituted one of the major central African polities of the eighteenth-
						and nineteenth-centuries.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0010">
					<form>
						<orth>Manyema</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also Manyuema. Collective group that, in Livingstone's use, encompasses the many ethnic
						groups residing in Manyema, eastern Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0011">
					<form>
						<orth>Masaai</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Well known African ethnic group based in the southern part of present-day Kenya and
						northern part of present-day Tanzania.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0012">
					<form>
						<orth>Ngoni</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group descended from the Nguni of kwaZulu-Natal in present-day South Africa
						who migrated north due to the Mfecane of the early nineteenth century.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0013">
					<form>
						<orth>Nyamnyams</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group of uncertain identity. The term Nyamnyam regularly refers to the
						Azande of north central Africa, but the context of Livingstone's use of the term in the 1870
						Field Diary points to a different group.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0014">
					<form>
						<orth>Nyamwezi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>East African ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania whose members often worked as
						independent traders or served as porters for Arab and African caravans.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0015">
					<form>
						<orth>Sangu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania and settled to the east and south east
						of Lake Rukwa.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- Current higest number = ethnic0024 -->

				<!-- 
			
				Groups that follow need to be defined.
				xml:id's are already in XML

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0018">
					<form>
						<orth>Bagenya</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0020">
					<form>
						<orth>Bakuss/Bakuzz/KunsBakuss/KussBakuss</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>


				<entry xml:id="ethnic0021">
					<form>
						<orth>BaziriWazire/Wazire</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0022">
					<form>
						<orth>Benya</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0023">
					<form>
						<orth>Malobo</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				-->

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
