<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 <!--Converted from a TEI P4 XML file to the LEAP TEI P5 Schema by James Cummings on 2015-03-02-->
         <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_000603"><!-- LP115 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letter to James R. Bennett</title>
                <title type="alternative">Letter to James R. Bennett, 26 December 1845</title>
				<author xml:id="DL">Livingstone, David, 1813-1873</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
				<date>2006-10-09</date>
				<publisher>Wellcome Centre for the History of Medicine, UCL</publisher>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_000603</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl xml:id="ccnumber">Letters, 0141</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="recipient">James Risdon Bennett</bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="date"><date when="1845-12-26">26 December 1845</date></bibl>
				<bibl xml:id="where">Chonuane</bibl>
				<bibl>National Library of Scotland Ms. 10707, ff. 21r-22v</bibl><!--1845-12-26--><!--Original:1845-12-26-->
				<bibl>4 pages</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>2006-08-07</date>
				<name>Sharon Messenger</name>initial transcription
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

	<pb n="0001" facs="liv_000603_0001"/><!--pb/@n='21r'-->
<!--hand1 top right 21-->
<lb/><p rend="right"><placeName>Chounane</placeName> 26<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> December 1845 </p>
<lb/><p rend="left"><persName>My Dear Friend</persName></p>
<lb/><p>As I have not yet <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> any answers to my last I presume it 
<lb/>may not have reached its destination. And as I cannot without an effort 
<lb/>afford to lose your correspondence I take this gigantic sheet in order to 
<lb/>stir you up to think on a poor "dweller in the wilderness" the longer 
<lb/>I am absent from home the fewer my correspondents are likely to become 
<lb/>And as you are in heart engaged to the same cause, you must not 
<lb/>leave me entirely to the wearisome round of news furnished in this 
<lb/>benighted region. We have wars &amp; rumours of wars untill the heart is 
<lb/>sick of them. Right pleasant indeed then comes the stimulus of a letter 
<lb/>from home. I have seen and was glad on reading a notice of your 
<lb/>promotion to St Thomas' and wish you every degree of success which 
<lb/>will be for your good. Your connection with the Sydenham society 
<lb/>a benefit which every one at home may enjoy almost made me 
<lb/>envious on the long weary journey we undertake I had my books untill 
<lb/>tired of their sameness. I should be glad if it were possible <unclear cert="medium">but</unclear> I need 
<lb/>long for what cannot be. We commenced a new station about 200 
<lb/>miles North of the <placeName>Kuruman</placeName> or <placeName>Lattakoo</placeName> and shortly afterwards I was 
<lb/>much injured by a lion. The failure of strength in consequence of a 
<lb/>profuse discharge from eleven gashes was so great I could not move 
<lb/>my limbs. And while lying in my little native hut I often saw you 
<lb/>in my dreams and I shall not soon forget the lively disappointment 
<lb/>I as often experience on finding that all surgical and was still on the 
<lb/>other side of the <placeName>Atlantic</placeName> When only partially recovered I had to begin 
<lb/>the erection of my house and a jerk <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> in lifting a stone 
<lb/>has led to a false joint in my left humerus. I often think of 
<lb/>putting a <unclear cert="low">seton</unclear> through it But never have been able to plan a six 
<lb/>weeks leisure. It is not however a great hindrance even in heavy 
<lb/>work - the chief inconvenience is the want of power to steady 
<lb/>the arm when extended. The <unclear cert="low">fissure</unclear> is oblique and being situated 
<lb/>in the upper third of the bone seems to run into the socket <figure><graphic style="float:right" url="lp115-1.gif"/><figDesc>image of an arm</figDesc></figure>
<lb/>the point of bone indicated at A starts out when my arm 
<lb/>is extended and the hand in the supine position and appears as 
<lb/>if it would burst through the skin But the biceps being situated 
<lb/>internally to it I could easily put the needle through I can use 
<lb/>the adze hammer &amp; lift heavy weights notwithstanding and if I 
<lb/>try the seton I shall let you know how it suceeds. But I 
<lb/>must not speak so much about ego. I shall give you a little infor
<lb/>mation concerning the diseases of this country and then proceed 
<lb/>to missionary intelligence. </p>
<lb/><p>Compared with other countries this has very few <term type="ailment">maladies</term>
<lb/>indeed. I have only seen one case of <term type="ailment">consumption</term> and only two 
<lb/>of <term type="ailment">scrofula</term> in a period of four years Amongst the <term type="tribe">hottentots</term> in 
<lb/>the <placeName>Cape Colony</placeName> the former disease is by no means rare but let 
<lb/>them come up to the dry and healthy climate of <placeName>Lattakoo</placeName> &amp; 
<lb/>they invariably recover. I am no <unclear cert="low">believer</unclear> on the curability of <unclear cert="low">Phthisis</unclear>the general But some cases which have occured have quite 

	<pb n="0002" facs="liv_000603_0002"/><!--pb/@n='21v'-->
<lb/>astonished me. One young woman I carefully examined and found no evidence 
<lb/>of her former disease although that had been pronounced by a medical man 
<lb/>well acquainted with the stethoscope as a real case of <term type="ailment">consumption</term>
<lb/>She bacame the subject of tumour on the ovarium and this having been 
<lb/>dispersed by iodine she is now quite well. Poor <persName>Mr William<hi rend="sup">s</hi></persName> of 
<lb/>Hankey was disuaded from coming up here. the medical men in 
<lb/>the colony having about as much knowledge of this climate as of the 
<lb/>planet Mars. I felt extremely sorry that he followed their advice and 
<lb/>went home to your cold wet cloudy climate. I <choice><sic>concieve</sic><corr>conceive</corr></choice> there is not 
<lb/>a better than this for patients with <term type="ailment">pulmonary complaints</term> in the 
<lb/>world. I have not seen one patient from either <placeName>India</placeName> or <placeName>England.</placeName>
<lb/>return unbenefitted by their sojourn. It is now in consequence 
<lb/>of the abundance of game to all sorts become very common 
<lb/>for Indian invalids who can afford it to make a trip up here &amp; 
<lb/>from their enthusiastic statement it is probable it will become 
<lb/>much more so. I wonder why the medical men connected with 
<lb/>our society do not recommend our Indian missionaries to come here 
<lb/>instead of going home. The East India company find <unclear cert="low">their</unclear> plan of sending 
<lb/>to the <placeName>Cape</placeName> good. The same plan adopted by our old society might save 
<lb/>a great deal of the funds. As I remember <persName>Mr Arundel</persName> once mentioning 
<lb/>that they considered you one of their staff I take the liberty of speaking 
<lb/>to you on this subject. And as I intend to make a series of observations 
<lb/>in reference to this subject I shall be glad of any hints you may 
<lb/>feel inclinded to give. We are if my thermometer can be depended on 
<lb/>nearly three thousand feet above the level of the sea. the climate is dry 
<lb/>&amp; clear and the nights are never so warm as to prevent sleep. the 
<lb/>winters are always bracing, and disease is decidedly rare. I have been 
<lb/>through the whole country and though well aquainted with the 
<lb/>inhabitants I cannot say they have more than three diseases at all 
<lb/>common among them. Neither natives nor Europeans are 
<lb/>subject <add place="above">to</add> any other maladies but <term type="ailment">opthtalmia</term><term type="ailment">indigestion</term> and 
<lb/>occasionally, a kind of <term type="ailment">bilious fever.</term> I have not yet 
<lb/>been able to ascertain in any part a mortailty equal to ten 
<lb/>per thousand. I have seen only six cases of <term type="ailment">Pneumonia</term> and 
<lb/>all these were infants except one. Only 2 cases of 
<w>Hydro-<lb break="no"/>cephalus</w> in native children and two in European infants have 
<lb/>come to my knowledge One only of these came under my own observation 
<lb/>the <term type="ailment">venereal disease</term> has often been communicated to bechuanas 
<lb/>but invariably dies out. <term type="ailment">Rhumatism</term> and <term type="ailment">disease of the heart</term>
<lb/>occur occasionally but surprisingly seldom when we think on 
<lb/>habits of the natives. In travelling they sleep on the ground &amp; have 
<lb/>but few precautions against damp. I have heard it remarked 
<lb/>that in certain climates injurious effects are produced by exposure 
<lb/>to the influence of the moon in sleep Nothing of the sort is ever 
<lb/>known here. I have myself slept for weeks on the bare ground 
<lb/>and often looked up to the beautifully clear orb until I have fallen 
<lb/>asleep But I have felt nothing in consequence nor have I heard the 
<lb/>natives ascribe anything harmful to her rays. If it is true that in 
<lb/>these countries <term type="ailment">malaria</term> acts with increased virulence at certain 
<lb/>lunar periods, the entire absence of effects at these periods in 

	<pb n="0003" facs="liv_000603_0003"/><!--pb/@n='22r'-->
<lb/><!--hand 1 top right 22-->relation to the production of disease would seem to shew that <term type="ailment">malaria</term> is 
<lb/>not abundant here. And that where it is in existence it is at least ponderable 
<lb/>&amp; acted upon in somewhat the same way as the tides. There have been 
<lb/>no epidemics except <term type="ailment">influenza</term> &amp; <term type="ailment"><choice><sic>hooping</sic><corr>whooping</corr></choice> cough</term> since I came into the 
<lb/>country - <term type="ailment">a kind of madness</term> previously unknown to the natives appeared 
<lb/>last year amongst the dogs. but it differs essentially from <term type="ailment">Hydrophobia</term>
<lb/>As a precautionary measure I have excised the bitten parts of all those 
<lb/>who applied for assistance, the disease appeared to be communicated 
<lb/>to a child &amp; a calf, both died. The long illness I was subjected to 
<lb/>by the lion and my subsequent building operations have produced 
<lb/>a great hiatus in my examinations &amp;c in the materia medica of 
<lb/>the country. Many roots &amp;c. have been spoiled by long keeping so 
<lb/>I must commence all over again </p>
<lb/><p>I have lately transfered my labours from <placeName>Mabotsa</placeName> to a new 
<lb/>station still farther to the North. It is a mountainous country but 
<lb/>you see a blank alone on the maps. The tribe is called <term type="tribe">Bakwain</term>
<lb/>or <term type="tribe">Baquane.</term> the country around is populous and away towards 
<lb/>the East densely so But as we descend the country is more unhealthy 
<lb/>the descent is shewn by the deep warm channels of the rivers <add place="above">rapid course</add> is 
<lb/>great But we hope to spread a knowledge of the gospel 
<lb/>even there by means of native teachers. I have two very 
<lb/>efficient men in connection with the new station, all 
<lb/>we have effected in this region may be called preperation only 
<lb/>We continue to gain influence and only a month ago two 
<lb/>wars were prevented by our mediation. <persName>The chief</persName> with whom I live 
<lb/>refrained from attacking the murderers of <persName>his father</persName> because said 
<lb/>he to them "I have promised to my missionary not to shed 
<lb/>human blood." This is an enterprising man. He built a stone wall 
<lb/>entirely round his town with loop holes &amp;c. and fruit 
<lb/>of his own invention. He had never heard of any <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> He 
<lb/>quickly learned to read, after acquiring a perfect know<supplied resp="#CO">ledge</supplied>
<lb/>of the large &amp; small alphabets in two days. Polygamy is the 
<lb/>great barrier. this chief often says "O I wish you had <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> to me before I became entangled with my wives." they can 
<lb/>form no idea of or rather they give no credit to historical evidence 
<lb/>because all they have <choice><sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr></choice> from their ancestors are a few 
<lb/>vague and unsettled notions. We who have had greater ad
<lb/>vantages can see <gap extent="1" unit="words" agent="damage"/> in these notions the fragments of a wreck 
<lb/>of their primitive faith but though we often make sure 
<lb/>of their own ideas in argument to the simple &amp; sublime 
<w>declara-<lb break="no"/>tions</w> of the Divine word have far more effect than reasoning 
<lb/>When we tell them of the great white throne and Him who shall 
<lb/>sit upon it they sometimes say "Stop now, you alarm us" But they 
<lb/>continue still in unbelief and nothing but a Divine influence 
<lb/>will change their hearts. may that be granted and the Divine 
<lb/>glory advanced in their conversion. </p>
<lb/><p>Towards the south the progress of evangelization is 
<lb/>steadily advancing. the fruits of the long continued labours 
<lb/>of our predessors are now apparent everywhere. I cannot 
<lb/>give any details as we have not heard from <placeName>Lattakoo</placeName>

	<pb n="0004" facs="liv_000603_0004"/><!--pb/@n='22v'-->
<lb/>for many months Indeed in reference to conveyance you are 
<lb/>about as near <placeName>New York</placeName> as we are to <placeName>Kuruman</placeName>. A misanthrope 
<lb/>who did not wish to hear any more about the civilized world would 
<lb/>find this almost as good for his purpose as one of the silent system 
<lb/>establishments in <placeName>America</placeName> But all will come right at last. 
<lb/>Will you kindly remember me to your honoured Father and believe 
<lb/>me. Yours ever Affectionately <persName>David Livingston</persName></p>
<lb/><p>Please address me care of <persName>Rev D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Philip</persName><placeName>Cape town.</placeName> It is 
<lb/>not necessary to send to the mission house </p><!-- No position marker needed since addSpan position marks text position --><addSpan spanTo="#addEnd-22v" place="end"><!--addSpan/@place='Sheet folded to make envelope. Envelope text on the middle of fol. 22v'--></addSpan>
<lb/><p><!--address on envelope-->Care of <persName>Rev. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Philip</persName><placeName>Cape Town</placeName>
<lb/><persName>James Risdon Bennett M.D.</persName></p>
<lb/><p rend="right">8 Finsbury Place </p>
<lb/><p rend="right">Finsbury Square </p>
<lb/><p rend="right">London </p>
<lb/><p>Single sheet </p><anchor xml:id="addEnd-22v"/>
			
</div>
		</body>
	</text></TEI>